Guide to the Chris Wheeler photographs collection
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Chris Wheeler photographs collection
circa 1910-1967
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Wheeler, Chris L., 1927-2013
Org. Lot 433
1.24 cubic feet 1 document case, 2 oversize flat boxes
This collection contains photographs and slides likely received and compiled by Chris L. Wheeler (1927-2013) during the time he served as state engineer of Oregon from 1962-1975. The bulk of the photographs depict the Tumalo Irrigation Project in Deschutes County, Oregon, from 1913-1915. Other photographs, color slides, and albums depict state and private irrigation efforts in Oregon from approximately 1910-1925, and dams and reservoirs in Oregon from 1950-1967.
Collection is open for research.
Gift of Stephen Terry, May 2008 (Lib. Acc. 26521).
Chris L. Wheeler was born in Milton-Freewater, Oregon, on December 30, 1927. He graduated from high school in 1945 and went on to receive a bachelor of science degree from Oregon State University in 1951. That same year, Wheeler began working for the office of the State Engineer of Oregon as a civil engineer and became the head of the office's hydroelectric power division in 1961. After the retirement of State Engineer Lewis A. Stanley in April 1962, Oregon Governor Mark O. Hatfield appointed Wheeler to succeed Stanley as state engineer. Wheeler served in that capacity until 1975, when the office of the State Engineer merged with the state's Water Resources Board to form the Water Resources Department. He later served as deputy director of the Water Resources Department and from 1981-1984 as the representative from Oregon for the department's Klamath Basin Compact. Wheeler died in 2013.
Sources: "Salem Man Named Engineer," Oregon Journal, May 18, 1962, page 5; obituary in the Salem Statesman Journal, January 12, 2013.
This collection contains photographs, slides, albums, and one negative, likely received and compiled by Chris Wheeler during his service as state engineer of Oregon from 1962-1975. Loose photographs in the collection depict waterways across the state of Oregon from approximately 1910-1925, including the construction of irrigation canals and the Tumalo Dam in conjunction with the state's Tumalo Irrigation Project in Deschutes County from 1913-1915. Color slides depict dams and reservoirs in Oregon from 1950-1967. The collection also includes four photograph albums, with images dating from 1912 to approximately 1922. One documents irrigation efforts by the Central Oregon Irrigation Company and the Deschutes Land Company Project; another contains official photographs of the Tumalo Irrigation Project. The third contains photographs that were collected or compiled by Oregon State Engineer John H. Lewis and depict canals, flumes, and dams across Oregon, views of the Klamath Project, and a steamboat trip down the Snake and Columbia Rivers, among other subjects. The final album includes scenes of the Tumalo Irrigation Project, the Umatilla Project, and various Oregon rivers and bridges.
Many of the photographs in this collection were probably taken or collected by previous state engineers, including Lewis (state engineer from 1905-1918) and Percy A. Cupper (state engineer from 1918-1922); their names appear on the backs of many of the photographs in the albums. Other photographers represented include Benjamin Gifford and Angelus Commercial Studio of Portland, Oregon.
Gifford, Benjamin A.
Angelus Studio (Portland, Or.)
Columbia River--Photographs; Snake River Valley (Wyo.-Wash.)--Photographs; Columbia River Highway (Or.)--Photographs
Irrigation--Oregon--Deschutes County--Photographs; Irrigation--Oregon--Klamath County--Photographs; Irrigation--Oregon--Umatilla County--Photographs; Irrigation canals and flumes--Oregon--Photographs; Dams--Oregon--Photographs; Bridges--Oregon--Photographs; Reservoirs--Oregon--Photographs; Rivers--Oregon--Photographs
Oregon; Photographs; Water and Water Rights
photograph albums; color slides; photographs
- Bay City Land Dredge operations, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Celilo Falls, Columbia River, circa 1915-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Crescent Lake, Deschutes County, Oregon, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Deschutes County, Oregon - Unidentified landscapes, circa 1913-1914; Includes one film negative and one panoramic photograph. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Rogue River Valley Canal Co. canal, Rogue River Valley Irrigation District, Oregon, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Summer Lake, Oregon, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Tumalo Dam construction, Deschutes County, Oregon, circa 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Tumalo Feed Canal flume, Deschutes County, Or., 1957 June (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Tumalo Irrigation Project canals, Deschutes County, Oregon, circa 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Tumalo Reservoir, Deschutes County, Oregon, circa 1914-1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Unidentified bridge, Oregon, undated; Includes original envelope containing photographs. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Color slides of Oregon dams and reservoirs, 1950 July-1967 September (Box 1, Folder 12)
  These slides may have been taken by Chris Wheeler.
- Album 433-1: Central Oregon and Columbia River water projects, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Contains photographs of projects by the Central Oregon Irrigation Company, including dam construction and canals such as the Pilot Butte Canal System and the Central Oregon Canal; canals built for the Deschutes Land Company Project; agricultural land and products in central Oregon that were affected by the irrigation projects; and the proposed site of The Dalles Dam on the Columbia River.
- Album 433-2: Tumalo Irrigation Project official photographs album, 1913-1914 (Box 3)
  Contains official photographs taken by an unidentified photographer or photographers during the construction of canals, flumes, and dam as part of the Tumalo Irrigation Project in Deschutes County, Oregon, from 1913-1914. Includes photographs of Superintendents Alfred Hanson and Axel Bye, Irrigation Manager Fred N. Wallace, and other engineers and project employees; visits by Oregon Governor Oswald West and Secretary of State Ben W. Olcott to project sites; and the project's headquarters at Laidlaw, Oregon (now Tumalo, Oregon), among other subjects. Includes two typescript indexes to the album.
- Album 433-3: John H. Lewis photograph album, circa 1914-1915 (Box 2)
  Contains photographs that were possibly given to, collected by, or taken by John H. Lewis, state engineer of Oregon from 1905-1918. Lewis's name appears on the backs of some of the photos in the album. Subjects include photographs of Tumalo Dam and other dams, canals, and flumes from various areas of Oregon; snapshots taken from the summit of South Sister and from other mountain climbing expeditions in Deschutes County; and photographs taken on an expedition down the Columbia and Snake rivers on the steamer Prospector; views of the Klamath Project; and other views of waterways in Oregon.
- Album 433-4: Oregon irrigation projects, rivers, and bridges photograph album, circa 1918-1922 (Box 3)
  Contains photographs of the Tumalo Irrigation Project, the Umatilla Project, Celilo Falls, the Gold Ray Dam on the Rogue River, the Portland Railway, Light, & Power Company's power plant on the Clackamas River, and bridges on the Columbia River Highway, McCord Creek, and the Sandy River, among other unidentified images. Some of the photographs in this album were taken by Angelus Commercial Studio of Portland, Oregon, and Benjamin Gifford. This album may have been assembled for or by Percy A. Cupper, state engineer of Oregon from 1918-1922, as his name appears on the backs of some of the photographs.